<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The charge of scandal and giving offence by conformity refelled and reflected back upon separation : and that place of St. Paul I Cor. 10:32 that hath been so usually urged by dissenters in this case asserted to its true sence and vindicated from favouring the end for which it hath beed quoted by them.</title>
            <author>Hesketh, Henry, 1637?-1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43451</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R227746</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12027540</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12027540</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52671</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43451)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52671)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 357:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The charge of scandal and giving offence by conformity refelled and reflected back upon separation : and that place of St. Paul I Cor. 10:32 that hath been so usually urged by dissenters in this case asserted to its true sence and vindicated from favouring the end for which it hath beed quoted by them.</title>
                  <author>Hesketh, Henry, 1637?-1710.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Fincham Gardiner ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Henry Hesketh.  Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>A copy at reel 528:1 is twelfth item in v. 1 of: A collection of cases and other discourses / by some divines of the city of London.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52671:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Charge of Scandal,</hi> And giving OFFENCE BY CONFORMITY, Refelled, And Reflected back upon SEPARATION.</p>
            <p>And that place of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32. that hath been ſo uſually urged by Diſſenters in this Caſe, aſſerted to its true Sence, and vindicated from favouring the end for which it hath beed quoted by them.</p>
            <p>
               <add>By D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hesketh.</add>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add>By Henry Hesketh.</add>
            </p>
            <q>Give none offence, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the Church of God.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Fincham Gardiner,</hi> at the <hi>White-Horſe</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:52671:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52671:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>Chriſtian-Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou art not ignorant (I ſuppoſe) that this Argument hath been han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled by a far better Pen, an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor that doth every thing he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes with that accuracy of Judgement, and ſtrength of Reaſon, that becomes a perſon of his Character; and therefore mayeſt wonder what ſo mean a Scribe hath to do after him.</p>
            <p>I have but this Anſwer onely to give thee; that it is neither affectation, nor conceit of this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that is the cauſe. This Diſcourſe was ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſome perſons, both friends to the world and the Author, who was wholly ignorant that the Subject was undertaken by another, and was thought fit to be ſtay'd till it was ſeen what that
<pb facs="tcp:52671:3"/> Diſcourſe expected then would be; with a deſign to ſuppreſs it wholly, had the Method or the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement been near alike: which becauſe it was not, and becauſe the ſame thing that hits one fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, may not do ſo to another, or not to all, it was determined to venture this to the Publick al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</p>
            <p>Which the Author doth with Prayer for, and true Charity unto all that need ſuch Diſcourſes; beſeeching God, that they may honeſtly and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially conſider what hath been offered to them of late, to ſatisfie all their moſt material Scruples and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, and that they may find a ſuitable effect upon their own minds.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52671:3"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Charge of Scandal,</hi> And giving OFFENCE by CONFORMITY REFELLED.</head>
            <p>THere are very few things within the Sphere of Chriſtian Religion, that more trouble and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract the thoughts of men, than how to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern themſelves, and order their actions with reſpect to things that are called <hi>Indifferent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In things that are eſſentially good or evil, or are made ſo by ſome plain Command or Prohibition of our great Lawgiver, all Parties are ſoon agreed; and there needs not any queſtion or diſpute between them in theſe: The Rule is plain, and (ſuppoſing men honeſt) there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be any great miſtake about them.</p>
            <p>But in things that are left wholly undetermined by God, and neither directly, nor by juſt and natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence either enjoyned or prohibited by any Law of his, there men ſail not by ſo plain a Compaſs, but have a larger Scope, and may more eaſily miſtake their Courſe.</p>
            <p>It cannot therefore be leſs than a good ſervice to men,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52671:4"/> to direct them ſafely in this Unbeaten track, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to them ſuch Rules, to which if they carefully attend, they can never fall into any dangerous errour.</p>
            <p>This is our Apoſtles charitable deſign in this Chapter; to which I ſhall have a reſpect in managing this preſent Argument, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. and by governing our ſelves by the meaſures of his diſcourſe in it, we may be able to hit thoſe great Rules of our actions in theſe things.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles diſcourſe is indeed but of one particular inſtance of theſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> the eating, or not eating things that had been offered in Sacrifice by the Gentiles to their <hi>Daemons;</hi> which I ſhall have occaſion to explain at large hereafter to you.</p>
            <p>But it is equally applicable to all things of the like In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different nature. And there are two Rules laid down by him there, which men ought to govern themſelves by in the uſe of ſuch things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Firſt is the Glory of God, <hi>v.</hi> 31. <hi>Whatſoever therefore ye do, whether ye eat or drink, do all to the glory of God;</hi> i. e. whatever ye do in theſe things, be ſure you have reſpect to the Law and Will of God, and take heed that you violate none of the divine Commandments, either by what you do, or what you refuſe to do in things of this nature. For this is the true notion and meaning of <hi>doing all to the glory of God,</hi> i. e. Keeping us cloſe to the obſervance of thoſe Laws and Rules that he hath commanded us. For then God is moſt truly glorified by us, when we expreſs a great ſenſe of his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty and Laws in all that we do. But this by the way.</p>
            <p>The 2d Rule is Charity, and reſpect to the benefit and advantage of thoſe we converſe with, and live among; that we neither grieve nor injure them by any thing that we do, or neglect to do: and this is the meaning of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52671:4"/> theſe words, ſo often quoted by our diſſenting Brethren: <hi>Give none offence, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that Rule of our actions in all indifferent things, which I have choſen to conſider in this diſcourſe: and the rather, becauſe we have ſome conteſt with our diſſenting Brethren about it.</p>
            <p>There hath been great talk about Scandal and giving Offence to weak and tender Conſciences, by Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Compliance with all thoſe things which the Church of <hi>England</hi> requires in her Liturgie: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the other Arguments and Pretences againſt it, this hath been preſt to ſerve in the Cauſe, either to add ſome real weight to the reſt, or at leaſt to add to their number.</p>
            <p>Though (to tell you plainly) I think it is onely to make a ſhew, and to render the bulk of their Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the bigger, that this is ſummoned to the Muſter, and not for any real weight that there is in it to ſerve the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>However, whatever there is in it, a great noiſe is made with it; and as a mighty noiſe hath been made about Scandal, and great pains uſed to wreſt the notion of it to ſerve mens purpoſes in theſe things: ſo great art hath been employed to accommodate it to the preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and to fright men with the guilt and danger of it, from complying with the Inſtitutions of the Church, which (as is pretended) are ſo very great a Scandal and Offence to weak Conſciences.</p>
            <p>Two great and popular Pleas againſt the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Ceremonies retained by it, have been theſe: tenderneſs and ſcruples of Conſcience, in ſome; and fear of Scandal and giving Offence to ſuch, in others.</p>
            <p>Some men have pleaded their own Scruples, and want
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52671:5"/> of ſufficient Conviction and Information, and excuſed their omiſſion of theſe things, from that ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſome have alledged their fear of Scandal and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending others, and pleaded that in bar of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance, from theſe words of the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Give none offence,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>How much the ſence of the firſt place is miſtaken, and how falſe the conſequence that is made from it is, I am not now obliged to ſhew. My Province at this time is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſecond, this place that I have now quoted: in order to which, I intend to do theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Shew that this place is not at all concerned in our preſent Queſtion, nor will ſerve that purpoſe that the Diſſenters from our Church alledge it for.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That if it were, it would conclude againſt them and their practice, in the preſent Caſe betwixt us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I begin with the firſt, which is to ſhew, that this place is not concerned in our preſent Caſe, nor pertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly urged by our Brethren againſt their Conformity to the preſent Rites and Uſages of the Church.</p>
            <p>And this I might do, from two things miſtaken great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the application of this Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The true notion of <hi>Scandal</hi> and <hi>Offence</hi> here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The nature of the things to which it is applied, which is vaſtly different from what men ſcruple or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear in our Caſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the true notion of <hi>Scandal</hi> and <hi>Offence</hi> that is mentioned in this place, and in many other places in the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>I do not intend here a large Diſcourſe of the nature of Scandal in the general, or a removing and rectifying thoſe many common miſtakes in the world about it; but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52671:5"/> only to obſerve ſo much as will be ſufficient to my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then I obſerve, that as there are onely two no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Scandal in the New Teſtament, ſo there are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two Caſes in which men are properly and primarily capable of being guilty of it, I mean in giving it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt notion of Scandal is, That it is a Snare or a Gin, by which men are intrapped and drawn into ſome plain ſin and wickedneſs. In which ſence it is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in many places, and particularly in that famous Speech of our Saviours, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.6. to 10.</p>
            <p>And men do then give offence, or ſcandalize others, when they do that which directly and in its own nature tends to induce others either to do that which God hath forbidden, and is a ſin; or omit that which he hath commanded, and is a plain Duty: both which men may do ſeveral ways, which it is not now ſo very needful to reckon up ſingly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond notion of Scandal is, That it is ſome juſt cauſe of grief or trouble to others in their Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an courſe, and that which hinders them from walking in it with that chearfulneſs and ſecurity that they other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would.</p>
            <p>According to which ſence it is rendred <hi>Offence</hi> in this, and many other Texts of Scripture, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſome juſt cauſe of offence, of trouble or grief given to another by ſomething that he ſees us either omit, or do.</p>
            <p>In this ſence it is uſed in many places of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, not for that which is a direct occaſion of another mans ſin, but a juſt cauſe of his grief and ſorrow, and diſcouragement in the way of Duty: So it is uſed par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.1. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.15. it is expreſſed by <hi>grieving.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this ſence men give offence to others, when
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52671:6"/> either by doing, or neglecting ſomething themſelves, they give juſt cauſe of ſorrow or grief to others, and diſcourage them in their Chriſtian courſe, and occaſion to them ſome trouble and grief of mind, that otherwiſe might be free from.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Having obſerved this therefore, I proceed in the ſecond place to obſerve, that neither of theſe notions of Scandal can be accommodated to our preſent caſe; nor can we be ſaid to give offence to others, in either of theſe ſences, by conforming to the Inſtitutions and Rites of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Not in the firſt ſence; for that can onely be in one, or both of theſe two caſes: either firſt, by doing that which is eſſentially and in its own nature evil and a ſin; Or ſecondly, by doing that which is directly a tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and a ſnare to induce another to do that which is a ſin.</p>
            <p>Now if it can be ſhewn, that complying with the Rites and Service of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is giving offence in either of theſe ſences, then I here profeſs, I will my ſelf immediately turn their Proſelyte, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Conformity, and proteſt againſt it for ever.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It hath ſcarce ever yet been ſo much as intimated, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> requires any thing as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Communion with her, that is eſſentially evil. None of our adverſaries (that I know of) have yet dared to charge her Doctrine with falſhood, or her Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline with any thing that is in it ſelf evil: And when any ſhall adventure to do it, I doubt not but he will find enough to enter the liſts with him.</p>
            <p>Even our bittereſt Enemies of the Romiſh Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion have dared to charge us no further in either of theſe, but onely that we are defective in both, and reject many things which the Church of Chriſt (as they pretend) hath believed and practiſed in the ancient and primitive ages of it.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:52671:6"/>
            <p>They would rather chuſe to call us Schiſmaticks, than Hereticks, or to prove us Hereticks; not becauſe we believe or teach any things for neceſſary Doctrines which are falſe, but rather becauſe we do not teach or believe all things that are Chriſtian and true.</p>
            <p>Neither do they charge our Liturgy, and Service, or Form of Worſhip, with any thing that is materially e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, no nor redundant, but onely deficient in many Uſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Rites, which they pretend to be Apoſtolical. And if our own Brethren muſt be more ſpightful and bitter againſt us than our worſt Adverſaries, let them look to it, that even they become not their accuſers at the great day.</p>
            <p>But yet (thanks be to God) they have not adventured to do this, and will be unſucceſsful enough when they do it; and therefore themſelves free us from giving any offence in our Conformity, in this ſence of giving of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, <hi>i. e.</hi> doing any thing which is formally a Sin our ſelves, and thereby inducing others into the ſame evil by joyning with us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither ſecondly do I ſee any one ſin, that Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is directly introductive of, or a temptation unto; and I will believe it will puzzle the moſt curious and inquiſitive to find out any ſuch.</p>
            <p>I have ſo much charity for my dear Mother the Church, and ſo much duty (I thank God) yet left in me, as to dare to juſtifie her from this imputation. I am ſure ſhe intends no ſin in what ſhe doth, nor knows of any evil, that her Communion will betray any man into.</p>
            <p>All that ſhe deſigns in her Doctrine, is to teach <hi>the truth as it is in Jeſus,</hi> and to keep cloſe to that <hi>Symbol of Faith, which was once delivered unto the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what ſhe intends and aims at in her Liturgie and Diſcipline, is by the one to keep men from innovating
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52671:7"/> and corrupting that Faith, or debauching it in their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and deteining it in unrighteouſneſs: And by the other, to direct them to worſhip God in ſuch a way, as is ſuitable to his own nature, and to the Principles of ſuch a holy Religion; and thereby conciliate that grace that may enable them to live ſo, as the Worſhip of ſuch a God, and the Belief of ſuch a Religion require, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige them to do.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, in one thing the Church of <hi>England</hi> may be an occaſion of a great deal of ſin in the world; but it is ſuch as will as little advantage our Brethren to have it granted, as it will be any diſparagement, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage to be cauſed by it.</p>
            <p>I mean, in being an occaſion of all that ſin and guilt that all thoſe bring upon themſelves, that rail and cry out ſo much upon it; that ſeparate and divide from it, and ſtudiouſly maintain and keep up an unreaſonable and downright Schiſm againſt it.</p>
            <p>But certainly all men will ſee that this is an offence onely taken, and not given; and ought no more to be objected againſt the Church, than Murther and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, Theft and Robbery ought to be charged upon the Laws of God, that declare the ſame to be ſin. Were there no ſuch thing as the Conſtitution of a Church, theſe men would not be guilty of Schiſm, and unjuſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from it. But ſo, if there were no Law, there would be no tranſgreſſion; and Adulterers may as well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the Law for their ſin in one caſe, as Schiſmaticks can accuſe they Conſtitution of the Church in the other. They are both in this caſe equally culpable, <hi>i. e.</hi> indeed not at all.</p>
            <p>In a word, and to conclude this Period; if Piety, and becoming expreſſions of Devotion in the publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God: If Gravity, Decency, and Order in the Offices of Religion; And if engaging men to a due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52671:7"/> and regard to the rules of the Goſpel, be ſins or evils to be eſchewed and dreaded by men; then I will grant that Conformity to the Church of <hi>England</hi> may poſſibly give offence (in this ſence of giving of it) but if not, I do not ſee any reaſon to apprehend or fear any danger at all of it.</p>
            <p>By theſe conſiderations it will appear, we are free from giving offence by our Conformity to the Rules of our Church, in this firſt ſence of Scandal and giving Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I proceed therefore now to enquire, if we cannot clear our ſelves ſufficiently from it in the ſecond notion of theſe things alſo.</p>
            <p>And this I think will beſt and moſt plainly be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, by conſidering what can be thought juſt cauſe of ſorrow and grief to a good man, or a reaſonable diſcouragement or hinderance to him in his way of Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. I mean ſtill, cauſe of theſe given to him by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Now theſe, I think, I may reduce pretty ſafely to theſe three Heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some diſhonour offered to God and his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Wickedneſs and Profaneneſs of men.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The making the way of Religion and Duty more cumberſome, and difficult than otherwiſe it would be.</p>
            <p>Theſe are great and juſt cauſes of offence and grief to a good man. It cannot but greatly afflict a good man to behold his God (whom he adores, and honours, and loves above all things) affronted and diſhonoured, his Laws violated, his Authority contemned and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon by daring and fooliſh men: <hi>Rivers of waters</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:52671:8"/> (ſaith the holy Pſalmiſt) <hi>run down mine eyes, becauſe men keep not thy law.</hi> Pſal. 119.136.</p>
            <p>And it cannot but be cauſe of the like ſorrow to ſuch a man, to ſee other men, for whom he hath a great and concerning charity, and whom he loves as his own ſoul, to live in ſin, and a contempt of God, to wound and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their precious Souls, and to provide matter for eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal torments.</p>
            <p>And any thing that diſcourageth a man in the way of his Duty, or renders it more perplexed and troubleſome to him, may be juſtly called an offence or grief to him. I do not eaſily underſtand how this kind of offence can properly be ſaid to be given any other, but by ſome of theſe ways.</p>
            <p>Now let our debate be determined by theſe things, and let the iſſue be, Whether Conformity can be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving others upon any of theſe accounts.</p>
            <p>It cannot, I am ſure, be ſaid, or at leaſt nothing like a proof be offered, that we offend men hereby, becauſe we either do any diſhonour to God, or to his holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by it: It is much truer, that we bring honour and reputation to both by it.</p>
            <p>To God, by taking the beſt courſe we can pitch upon to ſecure the Solemnity and Decency of his Worſhip: And to Religion, by taking care that all the great Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it be performed decently and to edification, and not profaned by the ignorance, or temerity of every bold and unskilful undertaker.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor ſecondly can it be pretended that hereby we let men be ſpectators of our wickedneſs and profaneneſs, and ſo grieve and make ſad the hearts of good men, while they ſee us without any fear of God before our eyes.</p>
            <p>I have that charity for the modeſty and integrity of our Diſſenting Brethren, that they will not call our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52671:8"/> Idolatry, and the ſervice of <hi>Baal</hi> any longer; though it cannot be diſſembled, that a great part of the leſs-diſcerning Rabble have been taught by them, ſo to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and think of it. But if any have been miſled into ſuch an Opinion, I would beg them to come, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold our way of publick Worſhip, for their better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. No, nor thirdly do I ſee how it can be any offence upon its making the way of Religion and Duty more cumberſome, or difficult to others, than it would be.</p>
            <p>It would be a hard matter for any to ſhew where he is hindred from being good, by ſeeing others conformable to the Church; or what obſtruction that caſts in his way of Duty. I will at any time undertake to ſhew, that it may be an help and advantage to him, and a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance to him in the way of Religion and Salvation; but let or hinderance it can be none.</p>
            <p>If it be pretended, that by this we make Religion cumberſome, and clog that with Rites and Ceremonies, that is a plain and eaſie thing; I grant the Objection were reaſonable, and the Charge of giving offence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable, were it either ſo as it began to be of old in St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s time, or is at preſent in the <hi>Roman</hi>-Church, clogged with ſo many antick and gariſh Ceremonies, that it requires a great deal of ſtudy to be an exact Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualiſt, and is a thouſand times harder to remember, and obſerve all the Rites and Modes of any Service and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in Religion, than to do the thing a hundred times o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>But let me beg men to conſider whether this Charge can be juſt againſt a Church and its Liturgy, which enjoyn but three Ceremonies, againſt which the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters themſelves can object, and theſe too not in the ſame, but ſo many diſtinct Services, and which are lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more than barely determining thoſe circumſtances
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52671:9"/> of Habit and Geſture, which are natural and neceſſary to all our actions.</p>
            <p>If theſe things can be thought to make the Practice and Services of Religion burthenſome, then any of the Poſtures in which our Brethren perform their Worſhip will make that ſo too; and then the Directory will be as chargeable and faulty in this, as the Liturgy.</p>
            <p>Theſe things will be ſufficient, upon this firſt way that I propoſed, to ſhew, that conforming to the Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church is not concerned in any thing the Apoſtle ſpeaks in this place, nor can come under his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of giving offence to any, which he ſpeaks againſt in it.</p>
            <p>I will not deny, but that ſome may be offended and troubled at it. It is too viſible how much ſome men are troubled to ſee a Church conſtituted among us; to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it protected by Law and Power, and to ſee ſo great a deference and reſpect payd unto it, and its way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (as bleſſed be God is at preſent) by multitudes both of great and good men. I do not doubt but it is greatly maligned and envyed by men, and it is little leſs than a continual trouble and grief to them. It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their private Intereſt, and ſo long as it is ſo, their deſigns and aims will never be effected.</p>
            <p>But ſo ill men are troubled at a good Government; and Thieves and Robbers may be vexed that Honeſt men are ſecured from them; and theſe may as well cry out, that the Laws and the Government are an offence to them, as others may, that they are offended at the Church and Conformity.</p>
            <p>Sure we know things better than to call every thing a Scandal that any man is vexed or troubled at: If we muſt acknowledge that an offence, or forbear doing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing for fear of Scandal, that every ill deſigning man is pleaſed to take exceptions againſt; it is more than
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52671:9"/> probable we muſt do nothing at all, nor venture to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake any thing, till we ſee whether all perſons will be pleaſed with it or not: We muſt not call every thing an offence that pleaſeth not the humour of every man; for then nothing can avoid that character.</p>
            <p>But this is not enough to ſay in this matter; for it will ſerve us much further, not onely to juſtifie our ſelves from this imputation, but to reflect it back upon thoſe that charge us: For when we have well conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed things, we ſhall find, that the Scandal will fall upon our Accuſers; and not Conformity, but Separation will be found to be the giving Offence, and that in both the notions of giving it that have been named.</p>
            <p>Separation is indeed the Scandal, as being both an evil in it ſelf, and that which betrays others into many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils.</p>
            <p>If ever there were ſuch a thing as Schiſm in the world, or if the Separation of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> or any that were ever made from the Communion of a National Church were a Schiſm, I think it hath been ſufficiently proved on our behalf, that the preſent Separation from our Church is really a Schiſm.</p>
            <p>And if Schiſm be a damnable ſin, (and ſo it is, if we will judge either by the Doctrines of the Apoſtles, or their beſt Succeſſors, yea and few ſins greater) then we ſhall need no other argument to prove Separation to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Scandal, and that in the greateſt notion of Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal too.</p>
            <p>And we ſadly ſee what great miſchiefs it is introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of; what uncharitableneſs and railing, what pride and cenſoriouſneſs it betrays men into Schiſm was ſcarce ever content to be alone. Men think it not enough to ſeparate from the Communion of the Church, unleſs they go to juſtifie their Separation, by aſperſing what they ſeparated from; and ſo men are inevitably betrayed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52671:10"/> into envyings and bitter railings, into ſtrife and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and all thoſe evils that ſuch things are naturally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive of.</p>
            <p>And I am ſure it is a ſore grief and trouble, and an offence (in the ſecond notion of it) to many good men, who cannot but be grieved greatly.</p>
            <p>To ſee the Inſtitutions of Chriſt ſo diſregarded, the great Duties and Services of Religion ſo ſlighted and neglected; and to behold the Peace and Welfare of the Church (which coſt the Saviour of the world ſo dear, and is ſo greatly beloved by him) ſo very little conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or rather purpoſely betrayed.</p>
            <p>To behold men allow themſelves (nay glory) in ſuch damnable ſins; deſtroy their Souls by the guilt of them, and wilfully forfeit the benefit of all that Chriſt hath done, and ſuffered for them.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, to ſee the way of Religion ſo perplexed with idle Queſtions, and made intricate by needleſs Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes; and to ſee ſo many unreaſonable Controverſies ſtarted, and ſuch eager Quarrels amongſt Chriſtians, which the beſt men ſometimes have much ado to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and get over ſo as they ſhould do.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the things that make many <hi>ſad,</hi> and aking <hi>hearts</hi> among thoſe <hi>whom God hath not made ſad,</hi> and theſe are the effects of the ſad Diviſions and Separations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us. Theſe therefore are the Scandal, and the things that ſo much offend, and theſe are the <hi>Diviſions for which there are ſuch ſearchings of heart</hi> at this day.</p>
            <p>I would to God ſome men would ſeriouſly conſider things, they might then poſſibly begin to reflect upon themſelves and their own actions, and perhaps ſee cauſe to take ſome part of that reproach upon themſelves, which they are pleaſed ſo prodigally to caſt upon us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But I have another thing yet, to ſhew the errour of applying this Speech of the Apoſtle to our caſe:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52671:10"/> For as there is a miſtake in the notion of <hi>Scandal</hi> and <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> ſo there is too, in thoſe things to which the <hi>giving offence</hi> here relates; and they are vaſtly different from thoſe things in the Church, that we conform unto, by which the offence is pretended to be given.</p>
            <p>The difference I mean is this; that however they may be things in their own nature equally indifferent, yet the ſupervening command from lawful Authority may make a vaſt difference between them. Thoſe things to which this Text relates, were indifferent, and undetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned too, no humane Law had taken cognizance of them; but the Inſtitutions or Ceremonies of the Church, in which it is pretended we give offence, are things already determined by the Laws of men, and ſuch as a lawful Authority hath bound us to the practice of.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not need to have any controverſie, I hope, with any about the nature of them; nor will any of the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Outcries againſt them prove them eſſentially evil. Though ſome men have been taught to call them <hi>Rags of</hi> Rome, <hi>Inſtances of Superſtition,</hi> and <hi>Relicks of Idolatry;</hi> theſe are words of courſe, and arts of railing, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim indeed the rancour and malice of ſome mens ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, but do not change the nature of things. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a ſtranger that ſhould hear all this outcry, and at laſt find the things declaimed ſo againſt are but pure Modes and Circumſtances of things, he would either greatly queſtion the judgement and honeſty of ſome men; or at leaſt conclude, that a little thing will ſerve thoſe men to quarrel with, that are reſolved either to find faults, or to make them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor ſecondly ſhall I need here to diſpute whether ſuch things may be injoyned by a lawful Authority in the Service of God: This hath been done fully already by a more learned hand; to which I have nothing here to adde, but that our Brethren, and all the ſeveral de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominations
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52671:11"/> of them, do the ſame thing themſelves, and ſufficiently confute their own Objection. So hard is it for them to frame any argument againſt us, which may not like a two-edged weapon wound themſelves.</p>
            <p>And time was, when ſome of them found it ſadly true; the Arguments that they had uſed againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> others galled their own ſides with; and they were forced to think thoſe anſwers good for them, which they will not allow to be ſo for us againſt them. And what dealing that is, I leave others to judge!</p>
            <p n="3">3. No nor thirdly do I think it worth the while, to ſtay to anſwer that trifling Objection, That this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of men alters the nature of the things; and ſure the Church of <hi>England</hi> thinks them more than Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, or elſe it would not lay ſo much weight upon them, nor make ſo very great a ſtir about them.</p>
            <p>It is a great miſtake, to think that the commanding of things indifferent makes any alteration in the nature of them; it alters them indeed with reſpect to us and our practice, but the things remain the ſame; and the Church commands them as things fitting to be done, but Indifferent ſtill in their nature; and ſo the Church of <hi>England</hi> declares them to be, after her commanding them: And her publick Declarations and Rubricks ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquit her from all ſuch thought; and if men will not believe her own Proteſtations, but ſtill pretend that ſhe believes contrary to what ſhe ſolemnly profeſſeth, it is but another inſtance of ſome mens ingenuity and candour towards her, and needs not be counted ſtrange in this Age.</p>
            <p>Nor is her ſtanding ſo ſtiff (as men ſpeak) for theſe things, any argument of her thinking otherwiſe of them: for however a Ceremony be in it ſelf a ſmall thing, yet Faction and Diſobedience is a great one, and ought with all care to be ſuppreſſed; and that Church needs not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52671:11"/> be blamed for its ſharpneſs againſt Diſſentions about theſe, which hath already by ſad experience found, that gratifying Faction in theſe, hath in the iſſue been the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter overthrow of her whole Conſtitution.</p>
            <p>If any Church may be excuſed in this, certainly this may, which hath already felt the ſmart of Indulging in them; and cannot but be concerned, when it ſees the ſame practices purſued again; and that too, by thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry men who trampled upon her with ſo much cruelty and ſcorn in the late time of her viſitation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The beginning of ſtrife</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>is as when one letteth out a River:</hi> and ſo we have found Faction in theſe things to be alſo; and therefore no wonder if the wiſdom of the Church apply it ſelf with ſo much care, and quickneſs to obſtruct the ſmalleſt beginnings in that, as men do to repair the leaſt breach in thoſe Banks, which keep in the waters of the other.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Nor fourthly do I think I have any pertinent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion here to aſſert the obligation of humane Laws, or to diſpute whether they oblige the Conſciences of men in things that God hath left undetermined: We need but conſult Scripture for this, which will be plain, ſo long as the 13 Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and the firſt Epiſtle of St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhall remain in the Canon, and not be expunged utterly by thoſe men, that truly would not be much more injurious to it in this inſtance, than they are in ſome others.</p>
            <p>But were there no Scripture for it, I ſuppoſe we ſhould not need to diſpute it with any men, that ever are in Authority. There are few of theſe that will permit their own Authority to be diſputed, or Conſcience plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt it, by their Children or Servants, or thoſe that they have the conduct of.</p>
            <p>And we are beholding to our Brethren for letting us know their minds in this: For no men have been more
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52671:12"/> rigorous in exacting obedience to all their Ordinances, and reproaching and puniſhing all that diſſented from them, as Enemies to God and Chriſt, than they know who in times paſt were.</p>
            <p>Never were Inſtitutions of men magnified more for promoting the honour of God, exalting the Kingdom and Scepter of Chriſt, nor men charged more ſtrictly in point of Conſcience with obedience to them. So that the crying out againſt <hi>becoming the ſervants of men,</hi> is but an artifice to pull down Government, which when men have once leaped into, they will by no means en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to be uſed againſt themſelves.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But that which I am more directly concerned here to ſhew is, that the things related to in this Text were not onely indifferent, but undetermined too: I mean, no Law had been made by the Church about them one way or other. The truth of which it concerns me to make out, not onely to ſerve my preſent purpoſe, but becauſe it may be ſomething queſtioned, from what we read <hi>Acts</hi> 15.29. where among the Canons of that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick Council, this is the firſt; <hi>That ye abſtain from meats offered to Idols:</hi> which ſeems to be the very thing that the Apoſtle is diſcourſing of in this place.</p>
            <p>And firſt, it cannot be denied, that in the beginning of the Apoſtles Diſcourſe upon theſe things, from <hi>v.</hi> 14. to <hi>v.</hi> 25. the ſame things are related unto, that are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by that Canon of the Council; <hi>i. e.</hi> the eating in the Idolatrous Feaſts of the Heathen, and of thoſe meats which they knew were by that Rite offered in Sacrifice unto their Idols. For the Heathen Sacrifices were not finiſhed onely at their Altar, but the Solemnity was continued and compleated by their eating and drinking together upon the remainders of what they had actually offered and conſumed in Sacrifice: Juſt as ſome of the Jewiſh Sacrifices (we know) were, from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52671:12"/> whom the Heathen tranſcribed many of their practices, aping them in almoſt all their Inſtitutions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But then ſecondly, that which he takes occaſion to diſcourſe of afterwards, and to which this Speech immediately relates, ſeems to be very different from what he had been ſpeaking of before, and which is the thing prohibited by the Council of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Which will appear ſufficiently, from theſe two Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Apoſtle here takes upon him a liberty to indulge a Latitude in theſe things; which be ſure he would never have done, had it been in that very Caſe, that the Apoſtles had determined before.</p>
            <p>And this we may be the more certain of, by conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the circumſtances of that whole affair, which (ſo much as concerns our preſent buſineſs) was briefly thus: The Jewiſh Converts retained a great veneration for the Ceremonial Law, to which they had been inured, and educated in the obſervation of: theſe being interſperſed abroad in many places, where many of the Heathens were converted to Chriſtianity, were greatly offended with that liberty, which they ſaw the others took in the uſe of thoſe meats which their Law prohibited as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean.</p>
            <p>This cauſed hot Conteſts, and ſharp Diſputes between the two Parties, to the breach of Chriſtian Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the great Scandal of their Religion. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles therefore are conſulted in this great affair; and having maturely conſidered, and canvaſſed the matter, determine onely to reſtrain the liberty that the Gentile-Converts took, in theſe three inſtances: <hi>To abſtain from things offered to Idols, and from things Strangled, and from Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as he was the Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſo he was the great Agent for them in this buſineſs, and the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52671:13"/> chief perſon that carried theſe Conſtitutions of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles unto their Churches; of which at this time the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> was one principal, and moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>Now it is not to be ſuppoſed that the Apoſtle would carry this Conſtitution and Order to them, which they ſo joyfully and thankfully embraced (ſaith St. <hi>Luke</hi>) and afterwards preſently would take upon him to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſe with the ſtrict obſervation of, and to grant a great Indulgence and Latitude in.</p>
            <p>This would be the ready way to expoſe himſelf and his Doctrine too, to contempt and cenſure, and to give cauſe for a ſharper reproof of himſelf, than he gave to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> for a leſſer matter than this was.</p>
            <p>So that we may be ſure, the particular matter here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated unto, was not the Caſe which the Canon of the Apoſtles had regulated, but that it was ſome other thing which had not been determined by them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And this we may collect alſo from the Phraſe in which he diſcourſeth this matter here in this Text: <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is ſold in the ſhambles, that eat, asking no queſtion for Conſcience ſake,</hi> v. 25. and, <hi>If any of them that believe not, bid you to a feaſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, invite you to an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment</hi> [for there is no <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Greek] and ye be diſpoſed to go, whatſoever is ſet before you, eat, asking no queſtion for conſcience ſake,</hi> v. 27.</p>
            <p>By both which expreſſions it is plain, that the Apoſtle here is diſcourſing of another matter than what was enjoyned by the Canon, or at leaſt of the ſame thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a very different denomination and circumſtance from that it is conſidered in there. For <hi>meat bought in the Shambles,</hi> and eating in the common entertainments of their Heathen Neighbours, are plainly different from the notion of <hi>things offered to Idols,</hi> taken notice of by the Canon.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:52671:13"/>
            <p>And this whole matter will be made plain, by giving an account of it, and ſhewing wherein the <hi>things offered to Idols</hi> intended by the Apoſtles, and thoſe diſcourſed of by the Apoſtle in this place, do differ.</p>
            <p>The <hi>things offered to Idols,</hi> forbidden by that Council were ſuch, part whereof was not onely offered in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, but was ſolemnly eaten afterwards as the Idols meat; and the whole Feaſt continued as a ſolemn act of Religion and Sacrifice, (as we know it was) and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed not onely as a Rite of confederating with the Idol, but of being more cloſely united unto him, and receiving a divine <hi>afflatus,</hi> and influence from him.</p>
            <p>And although the Idol to which this was done, was really nothing, and the whole performance a meer vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, having no real foundation at all in nature, and ſo poſſibly theſe meats might have been ſafely partaken of, by thoſe that were well inſtructed, and knew theſe things: Yet the Apoſtles thought fit to forbid them, for the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned reaſon of giving offence to the <hi>Jews;</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> enlargeth their reaſon in this Chapter; becauſe it was a <hi>confederating with Devils,</hi> and being <hi>partakers at the table of Devils,</hi> which he condemns as hugely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming them that eat at the Lords Table, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20, 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grotius</hi> is ſo exact in this matter, as to tell us there were two ways by which men might eat of things ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed to Idols, in the ſence that the Apoſtles mean.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Vel aliquid a Tabulâ,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> when at their publick Feaſts they ſent ſome part off the Table to be offered ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly to the Idol, and to entitle him to the whole Feaſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Vel ab Aris ad Menſam defertis;</hi> or when they took ſome conſiderable portion from the Altar, and fed upon it at the Table, as part of the Idols portion, as was hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52671:14"/>
            <p>Now for the Chriſtians to be preſent at, and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of theſe things, was that which the Apoſtles for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid in that Canon; and which St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo is ſo ſharp upon, from 14 to 24 of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>But that which he ſpeaks of afterwards, is vaſtly dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from it, and plainly means, either that part of the Offering which they afterwards ſpent in their ordinary meals, or which was publickly ſold afterwards in the Shambles.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe is eaſily underſtood, and was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon among them, to offer ſome part of the Sacrifice to their Idols, and to reſerve the reſt for their own common uſe; not looking upon it as ſacred, and the Idols por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as in ſome great and ſolemn Sacrifices they did; but that which was truly their own, and at their own diſpoſal, eſpecially having given a part of it to their Gods.</p>
            <p>The other, <hi>i. e.</hi> what was ſold in the Shambles, Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks give two accounts of:</p>
            <p n="1">1. It was either that which the Butcher ſold, part of which he himſelf had offered to the Idol, before he brought the reſt to the Shambles. <hi>Vel à Macellario, qui ante quam ad marcellum carnes ferret, aliquid de Aram in dediſſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Or that part which belonged to the Prieſts, and which they often ſold; having (it's probable) either more than they could ſpend themſelves; or perhaps ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a mind to exchange it for other meat, which they might purchaſe with the money they ſold it for. <hi>Vel à Sacerdotibus, qui partes quae ipſis cederent, venderent,</hi> ſaith the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>Now theſe were the meats about which the Apoſtles had made no order at all. So that men were at their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to buy and eat them if they pleaſed, without asking any queſtions, or troubling themſelves with any ſcruples of Conſcience about them.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:52671:14"/>
            <p>And which the Apoſtle commands them to abſtain then onely from, when knowing what they were, their eating them might wound the Conſcience of another, and they might <hi>give offence</hi> thereby <hi>either to the Jews, or to the Gentiles, or to the Church of God.</hi> To the <hi>Jews,</hi> by ſeeing them make ſo little a matter of Idolatry: to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> by encouraging and confirming them in that Idolatry, which they ought by all means to ſeek to wean them from: and <hi>to the Church of God,</hi> by ſeeing them ſo careleſs and regardleſs of the good and benefit of others, and without all charity to them.</p>
            <p>By all which I hope it is ſufficiently clear, that theſe things to which this Speech relates, were not onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different in their nature, but undetermined alſo as to their uſe, no Law having paſſed one way or other upon them.</p>
            <p>Now this makes them vaſtly different from the things ſcrupled among us, and by conformity to which Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is pretended to be given: For the uſe of theſe is already determined, and ſeveral Laws both of the Church and State, both of the Spiritual and Temporal power, have paſſed upon them.</p>
            <p>So that how indifferent ſoever they may be in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet it is not indifferent to us whether we obſerve them or not; but it is now matter of Obedience, and plain Duty; and theſe things are tied upon the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as ſtrongly as any matter of humane command is or can be.</p>
            <p>And therefore in theſe we cannot ſhew favour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence to others if we would; for we our ſelves are under Authority, and bound up by the Laws of thoſe above us. We have not the power of doing or forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor can we now abſtain for fear of offending ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man's Conſcience, without grievouſly wounding and worſe offending of our own; and whatever may be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52671:15"/> the conſequence of our Conformity, as to another man, yet we certainly Know, the neglect of it will be a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right ſin, and a grievous guilt unto our ſelves.</p>
            <p>So that in this matter the fear of giving offence to others is impertinent, a Snare, and a direct Temptation; and as improperly urged againſt Conformity, as it would be againſt any other Duty how neceſſary ſoever, to tell us that there are a great many men that will be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with our doing of it. In this and all ſuch caſes, we ſtand immediately reſponſible unto God, and may juſtly retort that ſo much abuſed and miſtaken Apology of the Apoſtles, <hi>Whether it be not right to obey God, rather than regard men, judge ye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But there is a ſecond thing yet incumbent upon me, and that is to ſhew, that ſuppoſing the Text were pertinently urged againſt Conformity, and there were a real poſſibility of giving offence by it, yet it would not ſerve that purpoſe that it is produced for by our Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Brethren, but on the contrary make very much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <p>And this I ſhall endeavour to make good, by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering who the perſons are that the Apoſtle here cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions us againſt <hi>giving offence</hi> unto; not onely the <hi>Jews,</hi> nor onely the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> nor <hi>both</hi> theſe onely, but <hi>the Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence, before I come to the main Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this place againſt the purpoſe and practice of our Diſſenting Brethren, we may take occaſion to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what the object of Scandal is, and who they are that men ought eſpecially to regard in their cares not to give it.</p>
            <p>At the time of the Apoſtles writing this, there were three different ſorts of men that might be offended with eating things offered to Idols: the <hi>Jews,</hi> the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> and the body of Chriſtians, which he here calls <hi>the Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52671:15"/>
            <p>In analogy to which, there are, and always will be, different Parties among which men converſe: Upon which account it will concern us to enquire, what our reſpects to them in this matter ought to be, and whether we ought to make any difference among them. And this we may reſolve our ſelves in, by conſidering the Caſes that concern us; which I think are onely theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When we perceive, or have reaſon to think, that what we are going to do will offend all Parties equally, then no doubt but we ought to forbear it. This was plainly the caſe here.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> might be prejudiced againſt Chriſtianity by this practice, ſeeing its Profeſſors make ſo little a matter of Idolatry, which their Law ſo ſtrictly prohibited, and God had always declared himſelf ſo ſevere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Gentiles</hi> might be encouraged and confirmed in their Idolatry, by ſeeing men of the moſt holy Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (as they called themſelves) conſent with them in it.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Church</hi> might be offended too, by ſeeing her Members have ſo little a regard to her Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the plain Canons of her great Founders.</p>
            <p>And therefore they ought to be extreamly careful and cautious what they did in this nice point; and ſo ought we always to be in ſuch caſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, it may ſo happen, that what we do may onely offend ſome. Theſe different Parties may have different apprehenſions of the ſame thing. Some may think it lawful, or a Duty; others may ſcruple it, or condemn it as a ſin. Now in this caſe it will concern us to conſider how we ought to govern our ſelves, and our actions, and what difference to make in our reſpects to men.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:52671:16"/>
            <p>And the Apoſtles Rule in this Text, will be a ſafe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and direction to us, eſpecially if <hi>Ecumenius</hi> his Note be true, as it commonly is in all places where a Climax or Gradation is uſed, as it ſeems plainly to be in this place: His words are theſe; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. conſider what the Apoſtle ſaith, how he puts the chief thing laſt, and makes <hi>giving offence to the Church of God</hi> that which eſpecially we ought to have a care of: and he gives this reaſon for the equity of this Rule, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. it concerns us to endeavour to win others unto the Faith, but by no means to offend and grieve thoſe that already profeſs it. And certainly nothing can be more juſt and reaſonable than this is.</p>
            <p>So that the ſum of this advice is plainly this; You ought, as near as you can, to do nothing to offend any; but however, take care not to offend the Church: You ough to have a charitable reſpect to all particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, of what denomination ſoever, whether <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles;</hi> but eſpecially to the <hi>Church,</hi> and never to give offence to that by any thing that you do.</p>
            <p>Now this will be a clear guide to us in our preſent caſe: and not onely acquit Conformity, from all guilt of Scandal, but caſt it wholly upon Separation, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to comply with the preſent Conſtitutions of the Church, ſince that is a direct giving offence to thoſe which the Apoſtle chiefly reſpects in this prohibition, <hi>i.e. the Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſtay not now to give the notion of the Church: I doubt not but all contending Parties underſtand that competently well.</p>
            <p>Nor to prove the preſent national Church of <hi>England</hi> to be juſtly called <hi>the Church of God:</hi> this (God be thanked) is fully done, againſt both the oppoſite Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions againſt her; thoſe that call her Heretical or Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52671:16"/> on one hand; and thoſe that reproach her as Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh and Antichriſtian, on the other.</p>
            <p>Were her preſent Conſtitutions to be tried by Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical and Primitive practice; her Faith to be judged by that of the firſt Centuries, and four moſt truly General-Councils; or her Liturgy and Diſcipline, her Rites, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, and way of publick Worſhip, to be compared with what we can collect and judge of thoſe pureſt times: Or were ſhe to ſtand or fall by the judgement and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages of the moſt able and learned of Proteſtant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines abroad ſince the Reformation; ſhe would not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be juſtified, but commended; not onely paſs for a true and ſound part of Chriſts Church, but the moſt ſound and Orthodox, the moſt truly Primitive and Apoſtolical of any at this day on the face of the earth.</p>
            <p>But I wave all this, and proceed to apply this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Rule of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to our own Caſe, as it is at this day, with reſpect to Scandal, and the danger of it, by conforming to the Church; which is plainly this.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> having reformed it ſelf from thoſe Corruptions that had ſullied the truth and beauty of Chriſtian Doctrine and Worſhip; not by Noiſe and Tumult, and popular Faction, which too much influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſome forein Reformations, but upon grave and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber advice, with the concurrence of the lawful Civil Power; digeſted her Doctrinals into ſuch a number of Articles, as ſhe judged moſt conſonant to the Faith and Doctrine of the Apoſtles and firſt Councils: eſtabliſhed ſuch a Form of Worſhip, as upon moſt diligent enquiry and ſearch, ſhe found moſt agreeable to the practice of pure and Primitive Ages; and retained onely ſuch Rites and Uſages as ſhe found moſt ancient, and freeſt from any juſt and reaſonable Exceptions and Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:52671:17"/>
            <p>All theſe thus conſtituted and framed, ſhe impoſeth as Conditions of her Communion, and requires Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty unto of all her Members. She will be grievouſly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended if any of her Children reject, and comply not with this Conſtitution, as knowing her Knowledge and Integirty queſtioned, her Authority deſpiſed, and that Power that hath confirmed all this, contemned by ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, there are ſome particular men, ſome Hereticks, ſome Schiſmaticks, ſome either deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or leſs inſtructed perſons, that declare themſelves of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by conforming to this Conſtitution.</p>
            <p>The queſtion now is, how we ſhall govern our ſelves, and which of theſe Conſiderations we will permit to ſway us: Whether reſpect to the Church and juſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and fear of giving offence thereto, ſhall engage us to conform; or whether reſpect to ſome private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and fear of offending and angring them, ſhall cauſe us to caſt off all regard to thoſe Laws and Conſtitutions, and all care to comply with them.</p>
            <p>This is the plain Caſe; and were there no other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations to determine us, (when yet there are many) I would deſire nothing plainer than the direction of the Apoſtle in this Text; where he tells us, that the perſons we ought chiefly to have a care not to give offence unto, are <hi>the Church of God.</hi> If ſome private perſons and the Church come in competition, and we muſt needs offend ſome, we ought to have a greater reſpect to the Church, than unto them. And were it truly giving them offence, (which yet it is not) yet were it ſo, I ſay, we ought not to attend ſo to that Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to caſt off all regard and care to the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This (I think) is a Rule ſo very reaſonable at the very hearing of, and ſo fair upon its own reaſons, that I do
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52671:17"/> not know whether it be really worth while to go to adde any ſtrength to it: We might venture it to its own ſtrength to ſtand or fall, and may challenge any one to aſſault or undertake it.</p>
            <p>Yet however, I ſhall proceed to enlarge a little more upon it, and to adde ſome Conſiderations which may make it ſomething more popularly plain and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And firſt, I deſire to have it fairly conſidered, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ought not to have at leaſt as fair a reſpect to the <hi>Church of God,</hi> as to any private perſons, of what cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter or denomination ſoever.</p>
            <p>I do not ſee upon what reaſons any perſon can deny this to me, eſpecially in a caſe where we cannot charge the Church with any plain degeneracy or open Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy from the Doctrine or Practice of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>When any particular Church degenerates plainly ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Doctrine or Worſhip, there I am not concerned to determine how far ſhe forfeits all that reſpect that ſhe might otherwiſe claim from men, nor how much the Credit of a ſingle perſon may vie with her. Perhaps when the Church was degenerated into <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> the judgement of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and ſome few other Biſhops, was more to be regarded than that of a whole Synod; and in the horrid Apoſtacy of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the ſingle Doctrine of <hi>John Huſs</hi> was preferable to that of the whole Council of <hi>Conſtance.</hi> But ſtill in both theſe Caſes (or any other parallel ones) that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect derived it ſelf not from their perſons, but was wholly owing to truth, and the holy Scriptures that ſtood with them.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God, this is not our caſe; our Church doth challenge and triumph over all charges of any ſuch Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy; and all the diſputes and conteſts with her by any of theſe men, are about things confeſſedly doubtful, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52671:18"/> ſuch as are in their own nature indifferent; things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which (to ſay the leaſt) it is as poſſible that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle perſons may erre and miſtake, as it is for the Church; unleſs in this alſo (as in many other inſtances) men fall in with the groſſeſt Tenet in Popery, that ſingle perſons may more reaſonably pretend to Infallibility than the whole Church.</p>
            <p>Every man derides, and thinks he can baffle all the pretences of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to Infallibility, and therefore ſhould bluſh and be aſhamed of his own ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther arrogating it to himſelf, or aſcribing it to another. For, the truth is, I do not ſee but his pretences are as juſt as another man's, <hi>i. e.</hi> indeed they are both monſtrouſly unreaſonable.</p>
            <p>And yet alas this is not the leaſt ſource of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs of this Age; nor need I be condemned for ſtaying a little while to drop a tear upon it. Men turn Dictators in Religion, and impoſe their own Dreams as magiſterially upon their Followers, as if they were ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; and I am perſwaded, their Diſciples hang as much upon their ſingle authority and confidence, and yield as abſolute and implicite Faith to all their Doctrines, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any poor Papiſts, againſt whom they exclaim ſo tragically for blind Obedience and Faith: They are kept in as abſolute ſubjection to their <hi>placits,</hi> and dare no more read and conſult Books that are written to inform them, than a poor Papiſt dare let a prohibited Book be ſeen in his Houſe, by a Father of the Inquiſition.</p>
            <p>If ever people followed their leaders blindfold, theſe men do: they will not hear any thing againſt them; They <hi>have their perſons in admiration;</hi> and I wiſh I could not ſay of ſome, <hi>for filthy lucres ſake,</hi> or at leaſt ſome mean reaſons equivalent thereto. They will not ſo much as ſubmit to means of Information; they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſay they are ſatisfied already; and the ſingle blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52671:18"/> of one of their own Rabbies, ſhall ſignifie more with them, than all the Arguments of the moſt Learned and ſober men living beſide.</p>
            <p>But I am inſenſibly drawn aſide from my chief Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, which is not to treat ſo much of a reſpect of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and Faith, as of Tenderneſs and Charity; which is certainly as juſtly due from us to the Church, as to any private perſons whatſoever; and it cannot but be as unreaſonable to fail in the one, as in the other. It is every whit as unjuſt for men to be more regardleſs of grieving and troubling the Church of Chriſt, as it is foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and unreaſonable to ſet up one ſingle man's opinion againſt that of many others, that are in the ſame circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and advantages of Knowledge, and every way both as knowing and as upright as himſelf.</p>
            <p>Whatever conſiderations there are to determine our Charity to ſingle perſons, there are the ſame (at leaſt) to make it neceſſary towards the Church, and as ſtrong reaſons to reſtrain us from offending the one, as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Whatever becomes an Argument in one caſe, is equally ſo alſo in the other; and if it be not as effectual with us, we are partial in the Law, and diſtinguiſh without any reaſons, but thoſe of our own partial and unjuſt reſpects.</p>
            <p>Let men be pleaſed to look into the Scriptures, and conſult the practices of our Lord himſelf, or his Apoſtles after him, and their thoughts will ſoon be reſolved in this matter; they will find the one calling for as much defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and reſpect to the Church, as to private perſons, and the other upon all occaſions as careful to pay it; and in all caſes extreamly careful not to give offence to it in any thing whatſoever; as were eaſie to ſhew in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances enough that are plain and obvious to all that read, and can ſcarce paſs unobſerved by any.</p>
            <p>This is the firſt Conſideration; and I appeal to all, if
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52671:19"/> it be not a very eaſie <hi>Poſtulatum,</hi> a very modeſt and reaſonable intimation: and yet (I aſſure you) it were a good point gained, and a very good ſtep towards our peace, were men hearty in their conceſſions of it. Would men pay but the ſame deference to the Church of Chriſt, and her Conſtitutions, as they readily do to their own ſingle Opinions, or the confident ſuggeſtions of ſome admired Leader, we might quickly hope to ſee ſome end of our Queſtions and Diſputes: And would they be but as tender of giving any offence to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, as they are of doing ſo to every little perſon of their own party, we might begin to hope, that the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our Church might gain ſome reſpect, and ſome meaſure of peaceableneſs and modeſty bleſs the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this Nation once more.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But this is too little to ſuggeſt, and the leſſer part of what I would propoſe to conſideration upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: and therefore in the ſecond place, I deſire it may be conſidered, whether we ought not to have a greater reſpect to the Church of God, than to any ſingle or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And truly I think this is as reaſonable a <hi>Poſtulatum</hi> as the other, and that which will be as ſoon granted true by all that duly conſider things. In all things whatſoever, the Publick requires more reſpect from us than any private perſon; and the welfare of the one, is to be preferred by us before that of the other.</p>
            <p>If the Church of Chriſt and any private Party of men come in competition, and it ſo happen, that we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably may give offence to one, we ought to let our regard to the Church ſway and determine us, and think it a leſs evil that ſome particular perſons be offended, than that trouble or offence be given to the whole Church.</p>
            <p>That ſaying of <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> recorded <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.50. though ſpoken with an unjuſt and barbarous deſign, yet is a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52671:19"/> certain and rational truth: <hi>It is expedient that one man ſuffer, and not the whole Nation periſh:</hi> And it is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a leſs evil to grieve or offend ſome private perſons, than to trouble and diſturb, and endanger the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole Church; which we muſt needs do, if at every private perſons pleaſure, we take upon us a liberty to diſpenſe with the Commands and Inſtitutions of it.</p>
            <p>And this is a Rule that not only all wiſe Nations, but even all men ſtill act by, in Caſes that are any way like to this.</p>
            <p>All Nations prefer the Publick good before the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate: and think it much better, that ſome ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſuffer inconvenience, than that the Publick be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered; and have ever ſet the worſt Characters up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe men, that have ſacrificed the good of their Country to their own private Ambition and Revenge; and never regarded what Confuſion and Miſchief thus bring upon it, ſo they may pleaſe and gratifie their own Paſſions. All the world hath ever hated and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached theſe as Monſters of men, and I hope we in time ſhall learn to do ſo alſo.</p>
            <p>Nay, we ſee nothing more common among the wiſeſt Nations, than to puniſh ſingle perſons for the correction and good of the whole; and many times to cut off thoſe, whoſe crimes in their own nature were not ſo great, and who ſeemed fairly capable of mercy, onely to be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples and Warnings to others, and to deter them from any thing by which the Publick might be endangered, and which were but the leaſt ſteps to the diſſolution of its Government,</p>
            <p>And we ſhall ſee all men act by this Rule too, in their own concerns, even any of our diſſenting Brethren themſelves. They do not ſuffer every particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to neglect, and ſpeak againſt their eſtabliſhments,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52671:20"/> but chuſe rather to puniſh and moleſt them, than endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger their whole Conſtitution.</p>
            <p>And they prefer their own Body, and the health of it, before any particular Member: they readily gaſh and cut one, to ſave all; yea, and will have a putrid and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified Member taken off, rather than it ſhall endanger the good of the whole Body. So true is it, that the more Publick good ought to be preferred to the more private, and that all men naturally yield a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the whole Society, than they do to any ſingle Member of it.</p>
            <p>And that the ſame Rule ought to be obſerved by us in our preſent Caſe of giving Offence, I ſhall endeavour to make evident, both by plain Warrant of Scripture, and by ſome proper Conſiderations, which all men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the reaſonableneſs of in other caſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I begin firſt with ſearching what warrant for this we can find in holy Scripture, either in the Precepts and Directions of it, or in the Lives and Actions of thoſe who are propoſed there to our imitation.</p>
            <p>And firſt, as for Precept and Direction, I think that of St. <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 6.10. to be very plain, and a firm foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for what I am upon: <hi>As we have therefore oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, let us do good to all, eſpecially to thoſe of the houſhold of faith.</hi> Where it is plain, the Apoſtle not only allows, but enjoyns us to make a difference in our Charity, and to ſhew this upon all occaſions, rather to <hi>the houſhold of Faith, (i. e.</hi> to <hi>the Church of God)</hi> than to any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons whatſoever.</p>
            <p>This place is full, and directly comes up to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Caſe, and the pretences made about it: For Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is as direct and plain a duty, as the not giving of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; it is as ſtrictly enjoyned as the other; and the neglect of Charity is as ſeverely threatned, as the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Offence is, or can be: And yet for all this, when
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52671:20"/> the Church of Chriſt, and any other perſons whatever, come in competition, and are Candidates for our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, we ought to ſhew it unto that, and not unto theſe. And the ſame reaſons that determine thus our Charity, will determine as well our care of not giving Offence; eſpecially ſince this is a proper and principal act of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and no one (that I know of) more ſo.</p>
            <p>This will be a ſufficient anſwer to all the tragical ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the ſin of Scandal, and the great neceſſity of not giving it to any.</p>
            <p>We are expreſly charged <hi>not to give Offence,</hi> and ſo we are expreſly charged <hi>above all things</hi> to <hi>put on Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In giving Offence, we muſt have a regard to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt perſon in the Church, and a woe is denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him that <hi>offends a little one.</hi> And ſo we are in charity commanded too, and a woe threatned to him that <hi>ſhuts up his bowels of Compaſſion</hi> from the meaneſt ſervant of God. Yea, this is commanded even to the creatures below us.</p>
            <p>And yet for all this, we muſt prefer the Church before all others; and if it ſhould ſo happen, that Charity could not be ſhewed unto both, we ought to determine our reſpects and Charity to the Church, and to ſuſpend the acts of it unto the others; and muſt do ſo too in our Charity of not offending or grieving the Church, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſome diſproportion could be ſhewed in this from the other acts of Charity, or ſome reaſons here to alter the caſe; which, I am very ſure, cannot. This place alone, if there were none others, ſufficiently determines this Caſe.</p>
            <p>And that we are warranted alſo by the Precedents of the New Teſtament to act by this Rule, the actions of thoſe great men whoſe lives are there recorded for our imitation, do ſhew us.</p>
            <p>The Life of our bleſſed Saviour is a good example for
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52671:21"/> us in this, as well as in all other inſtances of duty that are incumbent on us: We find him in every thing pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a mighty deference to the Church of the Jews, and ſtudiouſly avoiding to give any diſpleaſure or offence unto them; and this in many things which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves had introduced, without any expreſs Warrant or Command from God; as were eaſie to ſhew, and hath been by many learned men of late.</p>
            <p>But there is one inſtance which comes pretty well up to our preſent caſe; and that is his paying Tribute, of which you have the ſtory, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.27. there is no doubt but by this he might give ſome offence (in this looſe notion of offence) <hi>i. e.</hi> occaſion ſome trouble in his followers, by owning himſelf a ſtranger, and paying Tribute as ſuch; nevertheleſs he choſe to do that, rather than to give any offence to the Publick: <hi>Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that we offend them not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whether the perſons he was ſo careful here not to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend were the <hi>Roman</hi> Government, or the Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> it is all one to our preſent Caſe. If it were the Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> then we ſee he was more careful not to offend them than his own Followers. But if it were the Government of the <hi>Romans,</hi> it concludes more ſtrongly for us and for our preſent Caſe, where the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is Chriſtian, and that of the Church and of the Kingdom one and the ſame; where we cannot offend the Church, but we muſt offend the Government and Civil Power too, under whoſe protection and favour it is eſtabliſhed, and whoſe Canons it hath adopted into its own Laws.</p>
            <p>After this great example, I proceed to take notice of ſome that we find regiſtred in the life of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the like purpoſe. I inſtance onely in two, which will be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient.</p>
            <p>The firſt was his <hi>circumciſing Timothy,</hi> of which you
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52671:21"/> have the ſtory, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.1, 2, 3. It is certain, <hi>Timothy</hi> might have objected againſt Circumciſion, and pleaded his freedom from any obligation to it, being the Son of a <hi>Grecian</hi> Father; and there is no reaſon to doubt but it muſt be irkſome and troubleſome to him: yet for all that, St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath greater reſpect to the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> in thoſe parts, which might be offended, had he not been circumciſed, his Mother being a Jew.</p>
            <p>The other is that famous ſtory of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>ſhaving his head and purifying himſelf in the Temple</hi> with the men that had a vow upon them, juſt according to the manner preſcribed in the Levitical Law: you have the account of it <hi>Acts</hi> 21. from 23, to 27.</p>
            <p>I do not at all queſtion, but this action of St. <hi>Paul</hi> muſt be ſtrangely looked upon at firſt by <hi>Trophimus,</hi> and thoſe other Heathen Converts that came with him to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> who knowing his Doctrine, and manner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation abroad, could ſcarce chuſe but reflect with ſome trouble upon this action; and the truth is, it was a plain temptation to them to have ſome hard thoughts of him. Yet notwithſtanding this, St. <hi>Paul</hi> preferred his reſpect to the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and choſe rather to incur this cenſure of theirs, than to give any offence to the Church of Chriſt which was there.</p>
            <p>From which example a great advantage may be drawn, not onely to direct us what regard to have to the Church of God in general, above any private perſons; but even to a National or Local Church, which is but a member and part of Chriſts Church, and from which, the conſtitution of other Churches as to Cuſtoms and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages may be different.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> might have pleaded ſtrongly againſt this thing, to which St. <hi>James</hi> adviſed him, eſpecially upon the account of offence to thoſe that were with him, and to others from whom he came; yet for all this, his reſpect
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52671:22"/> to the preſent Church where he was, and his care not to offend it, overcame all other conſiderations, and cauſed him readily to do that, which neither they were greatly pleaſed with, nor himſelf in all probability neither.</p>
            <p>Which hath often brought to my mind, the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical temper of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> in that famous anſwer of his to St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Mother, which he magnifies ſo highly for Oracular and Divine; <hi>That at</hi> Millain <hi>he did not obſerve the Sabbath-faſt, becauſe it was not the uſage of his Church; but at</hi> Rome <hi>he did, becauſe it was the cuſtom there:</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing her in all ſuch things, to make the cuſtom of the preſent Church her Precedent and Rule, and by no means to give any offence to it.</p>
            <p>By both which notable Examples, we may learn by what meaſure to govern our ſelves in theſe things; namely, a reſpect to the Uſages and Conſtitutions of the preſent Church we are in, provided they be not ſinful, and plainly contrary to any Law of God: for of ſuch things I am ſpeaking all this while, and about ſuch things it is that our preſent diſpute about giving offence is by both ſides acknowledged to be.</p>
            <p>I onely add one thing more, before I leave this Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, That if we ought to have this great and over-ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling reſpect to any National Church of Chriſt, to which we chance to come, and in which we ſojourn, we cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ought much more to have the ſame to our own National Church, in which we not onely live, but were born and baptiſed Members of; and therefore ſuffer our regard to it to over-rule all other reſpects to private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that may interfere with it.</p>
            <p>Theſe things might be enough to aſſure the reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the preſent Conſideration; and I do not ſee what can well be objected againſt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And yet I ſhall proceed to ſome Popular Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations here alſo, which are owned for ſound and good
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52671:22"/> Rules to act by in all other like Caſes, by all ſorts of men; and which, when applied in our Caſe, will preſently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine it our concern and duty, to have greater care not to give offence to the Church of God, than to any private perſons.</p>
            <p>Four of theſe I ſhall juſt mention, and leave to take effect by our leiſurely conſideration of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That offending the Church, is offending the greater party: I hope, I may ſay, not onely greater than any other ſingle denomination of men, but than all of them together.</p>
            <p>I know how forward each party hath been to boaſt its number, and ſome to threaten Authority with their ſtrength; and to that purpoſe, to make falſe muſters, and great ſhews; to crowd together upon all occaſions, and to make it piacular for one to be abſent, when ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Party or the Cauſe was to be credited.</p>
            <p>But thanks be to God, that we have publick eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces now, and of late, that the Church-party is not ſo ſmall and inconſiderable as ſome men would have it thought to be.</p>
            <p>It is true, honeſt men are not apt to be noiſie and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous; the ſenſe of their own Integrity ſatisfieth them, and the aſſurance that they are known to God, is to them more than Ten thouſand witneſſes. They do not uſe to boaſt of themſelves, nor court greatly man's obſervance; they keep their ſtation, and uſe not to run from place to place; an art by which the ſame man may appear ten or twenty; and this perhaps hath made ſome good men fearful, and ſome others confident: But thanks be to God, they know one another better now, and have ſignalized their numbers to material purpoſes.</p>
            <p>Now this ought to be a ſwaying conſideration with
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52671:23"/> all ſcrupulous perſons in this caſe. In all others, it is thought ſafeſt to offend the leſſer party, ſuppoſing them but in the ſame circumſtances with others: And when a Diſſenter conſiders that by Conforming, he can but of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend ſome few of his own ſmall party, or at moſt but ſome few of others, but by his Separation ſhall certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offend the whole Church, methinks it ſhould ſoon teach him which ſide of the Queſtion to chuſe.</p>
            <p>Unleſs thoſe few muſt be counted the onely wiſe, and the onely good, the ſober and the godly party; and the whole Church be diſparaged, as conſiſting onely of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and looſe, ſilly and diſſolute perſons.</p>
            <p>When, bleſſed be God, plain experience contradicts both, and ſhews them to be equal at leaſt to their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilious accuſers, both for knowledge and virtue; and there is nothing to make them appear otherwiſe, but onely the Pride and Uncharitableneſs of ſome men, whoſe intereſt it is to have them believed to be ſo. <hi>But Wiſdom is juſtified in her Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Offending the Church of Chriſt muſt needs be of worſe conſequence than offending any private party of men. I need not ſtay to remark each ſingle inſtance in which this is evident, every man's reaſon will ſuggeſt enough to him.</p>
            <p>Neither God, nor Religion, can be ſo much concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the one, as in the other; nor can the Souls of men, or the peace of the World, be ſo much endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered by private offences, as by thoſe againſt the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church: Mens guilts are higher and more injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to themſelves, and the effects are more dangerous and miſchievous to others: which is another good conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration to ſway men in this caſe.</p>
            <p>For a wiſe man will weigh the probable effects of what he doth; and where an honeſt and uninſtructed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52671:23"/> man is uncertain whether he may do or forbear ſuch things, and after his enquiry remains ſcrupulous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolved, it is a good means to determine himſelf by, to conſider as well as he can what the effects and conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of what he is going to do or forbear, in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood will be; and that which he ſees attended with a train of the worſe, and more miſchievous conſequences, diſargues it ſelf, and pronounceth its own condemnation: And by theſe effects he may make as true a difference, as if the plain eſſence and nature of the things were naked unto his view.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Offending the Church of God, is offending thoſe to whom we owe more duty than we do unto any private party whatſoever.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, charity and reſpect, and all the poſſible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſtances of it, we owe to every private perſon with whom we converſe, and to whom we are any way related; and God hath made all this, matter of plain du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>But it is a great deal more than this, that we owe thoſe that are <hi>over us in the Lord,</hi> and his whole Church; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as much more as we owe of deference and Duty, of Obedience and Submiſſion to a Father and a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and thoſe that God and Nature hath ſet above us, above that common Charity and Duty that we are to owe to one that is in all reſpects our equal.</p>
            <p>The Laws of all Nations conſider us under greater ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to our Parents, and to our Country, than to any ſingle perſons whatſoever; and make injuring of a Father or our Prince, more heinous than doing the ſame to a common perſon upon the ſame level with us.</p>
            <p>And I am ſure the Laws of God, and Religion too, conſidering us as Members of the Church, and calling
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52671:24"/> the Governours of it our <hi>Fathers in Christ,</hi> let us know what great duty we owe to them; and of how much greater guilt it muſt needs be, to offend them, than our Fellow-chriſtian, or any Party in which we can be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged. There is a complication of ſins and guilt in the one, when there is but the breach of common charity in the other.</p>
            <p>I deny not but men may joyn themſelves to ſuch a Party, and make another man their Guide, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves to the Conduct of him, and thereby oblige themſelves to more duty than they owe to others. But this is duty of their own choice, and the failure in it a ſin of their own cauſing; and doth no more ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede their original and primer obligations, which God and Nature had layd on them, than the being faithful to a company of <hi>Banditi</hi> will excuſe diſloyalty to our Prince and Country; or than giving a gift to the <hi>Corban</hi> among the <hi>Jews,</hi> would atone undutifulneſs to a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Parent.</p>
            <p>However men may divide themſelves from the Church, of which Providence and Religion have made them Members, and enter themſelves into ſeparate Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; yet they muſt remember that they owe duty to it ſtill; that no voluntary and ſecond Compacts of their own, can diſſolve their primitive Obligations; or their care to continue faithful to the one, expiate their regardleſs offending of the other: for they do owe more duty to the one than to the other; what they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to owe to one, is contracted by themſelves; but what they owe to the other, is bound on them by the ſacred and ſtrong ties of Religion and Providence.</p>
            <p>And this is another good Argument to determine a ſcrupulous perſon in this matter: If he be in doubt which he had beſt to offend, the Church of Chriſt, or his own private Party, and know not by what conſiderations to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52671:24"/> determine his reſolution; let him in Gods name conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to which he owes moſt, what the Laws of God make his duty to the one more than to the other; and then, if he be honeſt and ſingle-eyed, he will ſoon be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reſolve his ſcruple, and know what choice he ought to make.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Offending the Church of God is truly a grievous Scandal, and an Offence, in the true Goſpel-notion of it; but the offending particular perſons may poſſibly not be ſo.</p>
            <p>That which I mean is this; the Church of God we may be ſure will not take offence but upon juſt reaſon; but other men may call that an offence to them, which really is not. If we do that which grieves and injureth the whole Church, then we do properly offend, and are guilty of Scandal in the true notion of it. But if we onely offend ſome private perſons of our own party, they may call that an offence which is not ſo: For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very grieving (and offending of another in that ſenſe of the word) is not a formal Scandal, as I hinted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and hath been ſince this, made clear by a better Pen.</p>
            <p>And to apply this to our preſent matter in debate, this is really ſo in our Caſe of Conformity: the refuſal of it, and ſeparating our ſelves from the Communion of the Church, is truly that giving of offence which the Goſpel condemns; it is laying a ſnare in the way of men, intrapping them into that damnable ſin of Schiſm; it is an obſtructing the effect of Religion, and a direct hinderance of that Concord and Love, that U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity and Peace, that it ſo ſtrictly calls for among Chriſtians, and deſignes to render the World happy by.</p>
            <p>But you may challenge any diſſenting perſon to ſhew
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52671:25"/> how angring ſome private perſons, and a ſingle party of Schiſmaticks, can be a Scandal to them; or to name any one ſin that it is temptation to them to commit, and to inſtance that prejudice or diſſervice that it doth to Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>It is poſſible (I muſt confeſs) that grief and anger at ſuch a perſons Conformity, may irritate and provoke men to ſome things that are evil. But then I ſay that this is the fault of them that are angry, and not his, with whom they are cauſeleſly offended; it may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an offence on their parts, but not giving it by him. For if we muſt call every thing an offence, that any man doth pervert into an occaſion of evil, there will ſcarce any, no not the beſt actions of men, eſcape that denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>This methinks is a very material conſideration, and ought always to ſway with men in this Caſe; and if men could not determine themſelves in it by other Reaſons, yet they might by this: They ſhould conſider which is moſt likely to judge trueſt what is Scandal, and what is not; and when both ſides ſay they are offended, which is likely to be ſo indeed.</p>
            <p>Particular perſons, and Parties of men may miſtake, and it is notorious, often do call that an Offence and Scandal, which is not ſo. But the whole Church is not ſo like to take cognizance of, and be offended publickly with any thing which doth not deſerve that name. To which we may caſt in this conſideration, to add weight to the other: Every offence to a ſingle private perſon or perſons, is not the ſin of Scandal; but no man can offend the Church of God, but he ſins grievouſly, and is directly guilty of a great Scandal.</p>
            <p>To conclude, the ſum of all that I would have conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered on this Subject, is this.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:52671:25"/>1. That the fear of giving offence to weak and unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed perſons by Conformity to our Church, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to the Communion of it, is cauſeleſs, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without any juſt reaſon: Conformity being neither a ſin, nor cauſal of any, nor any juſt cauſe of offence to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is now matter of plain and indiſpenſible duty, tied on us by the Commands and Laws both of God and man, and therefore carefully to be done, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may be the conſequences of it to others: That no ſnares or poſſibilities of offence to ſome men by it ought to ſuperſede our care, or can atone the ſin of negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of it: That we cannot forbear it now, for fear of offending others, without grievouſly offending our ſelves, and our own Conſciences.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That our refuſing to Conform, will greatly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Church of God; and indeed it doth ſo: Not onely our own National Church of <hi>England,</hi> but even all the Reformed Churches abroad too, as may be ſeen in ſome Declarations of the Great men among them of late, who cannot but grieve to ſee their great Bulwark, and the whole Reformation, ſo battered and weakned by this means, and ſuch great advantage thereby given to the great Enemy againſt it.</p>
            <p>And therefore that this conſideration ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponderate all the ſcruples and fears, and fancied poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of giving offence to private perſons of our own party by it.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, that the effect of all this, diſcover it ſelf in a ſpeedy conſcientious care, and honeſt endeavour to put a period to our cauſeleſs Separations and Diviſions, which are the onely true Scandal and giving Offence that I know of in this Caſe.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:52671:26"/>
            <p>That we no longer go on madly to contrive our own Ruine, in pulling down thoſe Walls, and making thoſe Breaches in our Churches Banks, at which the Enemy may, and, without Gods immediate interpoſition, will ſuddenly break in as a mighty reſiſtleſs torrent.</p>
            <p>That we may all of us return to the Communion of the Church, whoſe Doctrine is Orthodox, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Apoſtolical, and whoſe terms of Communion none of us dare term ſinful: In which we may accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſerve our God, and happily ſave our own Souls; live happily, and die comfortably, and paſs into the Communion of that Church Triumphant above, which ſings inceſſant Hallelujahs to God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt. To whom let us alſo give all poſſible praiſe and Thankſgiving, both now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:52671:26"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>FINCHAM GARDINER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Continuation and Vindication of the Defence of Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Unreaſonableneſs of Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lob, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſiderations of preſent uſe, conſidering the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger reſulting from the change of our Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Perſwaſive to Communion with the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. A Reſolution of ſome Caſes of Conſcience which reſpect Church-Communion.</item>
               <item>3. The Caſe of Indifferent things uſed in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, propoſed and Stated, by conſidering theſe Queſtions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. A Diſcourſe about Edification.</item>
               <item>5. The Reſolution of this Caſe of Conſcience, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church of</hi> Englands <hi>Symbolizing ſo far as it doth with the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>makes it unlawful to hold Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church of</hi> England?</item>
               <item>6. A Letter to <hi>Anonymus,</hi> in anſwer to his three Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> about Church-Communion.</item>
               <item>7. Certain Caſes of Conſcience reſolved, concerning the Lawfulneſs of joyning with Forms of Prayer in Publick Worſhip. In two Parts.</item>
               <item>8. The Caſe of mixt Communion: Whether it be Lawful to Separate from a Church upon the account of promiſcuous Congregations and mixt Communions?</item>
               <item>9. An Anſwer to the Diſſenters Objections againſt the Common Prayers, and ſome other parts of Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice preſcribed in the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10. The Caſe of Kneeling at the Holy Sacrament ſtated and reſolved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The firſt Part.</item>
               <item>11. Certain Caſes of Conſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſecond Part.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:52671:27"/>
               <item>12. A Diſcourſe of Profiting by Sermons, and of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to hear where men think they can profit moſt.</item>
               <item>13. A ſerious Exhortation, with ſome important Advices, relating to the late Caſes about Conformity, recommended to the preſent Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>14. An Argument for Union; taken from the true intereſt of thoſe Diſſenters in <hi>England</hi> who profeſs and call themſelves Proteſtants.</item>
               <item>15. The Caſe of Kneeling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Second Part.</item>
               <item>16. Some Conſiderations about the Caſe of Scandal, or giving Offence to Weak Brethren.</item>
               <item>17. The Caſe of Infant-Baptiſm, in Five Queſtions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. A Diſcourſe about the charge of Novelty upon the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> made by the Papiſts asking of us the Queſtion, Where was our Religion before <hi>Luther?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. A Diſcourſe about Tradition, ſhewing what is meant by it, and what Tradition is to be received, and what Tradition is to be rejected.</item>
                     <item>3. The difference of the Caſe between the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Proteſtants from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Separation of Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. The Proteſtant Reſolution of Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
